[SPEAKER_00]: So, here are the few excerpts from Manjumanikāya, and mostly it's from Mūla Pāryāya Sutta, the number one.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is on a difference between Putujana, Ārya Sāvaka, and an arahant conceiving.
[SPEAKER_00]: Here, because an untaught ordinary person who does not see the noble ones, who is unskilled and untrained in noble ones' dhamma, who does not see good men, who is unskilled and untrained in good men's dhamma, from earth he perceives earth.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having perceived earth from earth, he conceives earth, he conceives in earth, he conceives from earth, he conceives earth as mine, he delights in earth.
[SPEAKER_00]: For what reason?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because he has not fully understood it, I say.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, here, obviously, earth, the element of earth, well, pretty much can stand for anything, any phenomena that arises in the experience of Bhutujana through his senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, anything that's perceivable, anything that's perceivable can be discerned back down to the fundamental presence of the four elements, one among them or so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, having perceived sight from sight, he conceives his sight, he conceives in sight, he conceives from sight, he conceives sight as mine, he delights in sight, because he hasn't fully understood it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, on that very fundamental level of perception, of putrujana's perception of his sight, sound, smell, taste, touches,
[SPEAKER_00]: That's already where he conceives it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where, where the mistake is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, this is not, this is not a momentary thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: A sight of puthujjana does not last only for a split second.
[SPEAKER_00]: A sight is an experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a, it's a phenomenological experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you have a sight of something agreeable, of something disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_00]: You've seen something agreeable and disagreeable, and now your mind revolves around it, for example.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that, that sight is present throughout.
[SPEAKER_00]: For the whole time, it endures.
[SPEAKER_00]: As the Buddha would say, it's changing while standing, the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not that Bhutujana must uproot this subconscious momentary flux of his consciousness and sights and whatnot.
[SPEAKER_00]: He needs to... needs to understand the nature of the seen, the nature of the heard, the nature of the sense in any other way.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's... that's the famous bhagya-sutta.
[SPEAKER_00]: In seen, there will be just the seen, when it's fully understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, when it's not fully understood, he conceives the seen, he conceives in the seen, from the seen, he conceives seen as mine, and he delights in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there is no understanding of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's another... another reason to be wary of... of meditation practices that sort of... make people jump right into sort of like observation of sensations and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Knowingly, like for Pūtūjana, because if Pūtūjana spends time with his observation, he's spending time with his own conceivings.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, just perceiving things through your senses cannot reveal you the truth, because that's exactly the problem here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pūtūjana is just perceiving earth as earth, but because of that, he conceives it.
[SPEAKER_00]: His perception is not full understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what Pūtūjana perceives cannot undo his state of Pūtūjana.
[SPEAKER_00]: Only what Putujana understands can undo his state of Putujana.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if a meditation technique or practice is about just perceiving sensations in your body, in your feet and so on, that has nothing to do with understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you are perceiving things ignorantly with your ignorance, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: It comes down to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, perception cannot free a Putujana.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter what... even he perceives nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: And actually, there are the suttas that say that.
[SPEAKER_00]: He perceives nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: He thinks this nibbāna is mine and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And Buddha said, yeah, that is nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: But because he doesn't understand it, he doesn't attain it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's about understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's about understanding of the... of the five senses, the nature of it, the manifestation of the sight, sound, smell, taste, touches.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not about perceiving the... the microscopic little sort of quick moments and catching them in their flux.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter what Putujana perceives, his ignorance is there with that perception, because it's in the perception.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why this sutta is called the root of all things, Mūla Pāryāya Sutta.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means, no matter how far
[SPEAKER_00]: Bhūtujana's perceptions kind of ranges how far it goes, how subtle it becomes.
[SPEAKER_00]: It cannot go below earth, water, fire and air as the four fundamental elements.
[SPEAKER_00]: And even if he were to perceive them, he will be conceiving them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the problem is not in the content.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not in earth, water, fire, air.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not in the sight, sound, smell, taste, touch, thoughts, for that matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: The problem is in his perception.
[SPEAKER_00]: It hasn't been understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because of that, it conceives.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the fundamental difference between Putujana and Ārya-sāvaka.
[SPEAKER_00]: Says Bhikkhu, who is a trainee, who is Ārya-sāvaka, who still dwells aspiring for the unsurpassed security from bondage.
[SPEAKER_00]: From earth, he directly knows earth.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, that's the fundamental difference.
[SPEAKER_00]: Satipaṭṭhāna, or higher, has understood, has understood the nature of things, has understood the nature of suffering, has understood the nature of perception, has understood the nature of earth, water, fire and air.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's understood the nature of the appearing phenomena.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because of that, he's free from from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Four Noble Truths are understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: By knowing the way out of suffering, you are free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of course, an ārya-sāvaka,
[SPEAKER_00]: As to stop now, or rather, make the effort of renunciation in regard to the habits that still linger from his previous ignorance, that now has been destroyed,
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he's encouraged to not conceive Earth.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's encouraged to not conceive in Earth.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's encouraged to not conceive from the Earth, and he's encouraged to not conceive Earth as mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that encouragement can work for him, because he has that reference point of having understood the Earth, directly knows the Earth, which is what's in common with Ārya-sāvaka and Arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, for as long as he doesn't... for as long as he, eh... fully doesn't develop the not conceiving in earth, from earth, earth is mine, for as long as he doesn't fully surmount the delighting in earth, inside sounds, smells, tastes, touches, he will, eh... he will still be subjected to... to the leftover symptoms of his previous illness of being a putujana.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the illness is uprooted.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if he doesn't necessarily make much effort in this life, as the Buddha said, at seven most times, seven most occurrences of his lives, the work will be seen through by the end of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But why wait?
[SPEAKER_00]: If he can sort of uproot, overcome, extinguish all the lingering symptoms,
[SPEAKER_00]: From his prior infection with avijja, he should do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then it says, Bhikkhu, who is an arahant, with taints destroyed, who has lived a holy life, has done what had to be done, laying down the burden, reached his goal, destroyed the fetters of being.
[SPEAKER_00]: From earth, he directly knows earth.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same, same like an ārya sāvaka, same like a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_00]: But he's also liberated from these, from all the fetters, because from Earth, having directly known Earth, he does not conceive it.
[SPEAKER_00]: He does not conceive in Earth.
[SPEAKER_00]: He does not conceive from Earth.
[SPEAKER_00]: He doesn't conceive Earth is mine and he doesn't delight in it, because he has fully understood it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's not much to add really to that, but it's obvious.
[SPEAKER_00]: First, the earth, the phenomenon that has arisen in the experience, needs to be understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether you pin it down to earth, water, fire and air, whether sight, sound, smell, taste, touch, needs to be directly known.
[SPEAKER_00]: It cannot be just perceived.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the important point here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because people would often think it's a question of perceiving special things, novelty things, subtle things, and that's how you discover the sub-truths or some hidden realities behind.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it doesn't get more hidden than the fundamental great elements of earth, water, fire and air.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, even if those things are perceived, ignorance is there, because ignorance is in that perception.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, for an arahant, who has fully understood it, or rather, who is directly... who directly knows it, as the Sutta says, in the same sense Sotāpanna directly knows it, but then arahant also made the effort and extinguished all the symptoms of conceiving, of lingering conceiving, which are kind of gratuitous for an ārya-sāvaka.
[SPEAKER_00]: The main... the main dart of ignorance, the main poisonous sort of infection.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's done.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's uprooted.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now, he just needs to wait for the wound to heal.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what we would encourage here.
[SPEAKER_00]: In order for a wound of sotāpanna to heal, like the previous wound of being a putujana, he needs to stop conceiving.
[SPEAKER_00]: Make the effort and actually withdraw the conceivings that he might still habitually... well, he will habitually have to a different degree.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, the second bit is the difference between the three in terms of what they attend to.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's obviously connected to this, so...
[SPEAKER_00]: Here, because an untaught ordinary person, a patujana, who does not see noble ones and is unskilled and untrained in their dhamma, who does not see good men and is unskilled and undisciplined in their dhamma, does not understand what things should be attended to and what things should not be attended to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Since that is so, he attends to those things he should not attend to, and he does not attend to those things he should attend to.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, eh... again, so, it's not a question of just, eh... taking for granted what you've been told you must pay attention to, such as bodily sensations and various types of perception.
[SPEAKER_00]: The question is understanding the nature of what should be attended, as in skillful and wholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: And what should not be attended, as in unskillful, unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, in order for... like, you don't perceive, necessarily.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't perceive skillfulness of a skillful thing, nor unskillfulness of an unskillful thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can know it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can come to those... those... those discernments after... after the effort has been made to be understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, why is a wholesome thing wholesome?
[SPEAKER_00]: And what makes a... sometimes something seemingly unwholesome is actually wholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, for somebody who never practiced restraint, saying no to sensual desire and everything can... is very very unpleasant initially, and very painful, and it can seem very counterintuitive as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's going against the nature, against the human mind, against the body, against everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's a wholesome thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, torturing your body, and like extreme forms of asceticism, on a verge of death,
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is like taking that against the body to the extreme.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that becomes unwholesome as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, things are not necessarily defined by perception, in terms of whether they're wholesome or unwholesome, but that can be understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If one understands that, one can attend to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: One knows what to attend.
[SPEAKER_00]: And as the Buddha said, Putujana does not understand what should be attended to.
[SPEAKER_00]: He doesn't understand.
[SPEAKER_00]: He might have faith in it, he might have heard an instruction and now he's attending to it, to these things, but even so, if it were to be done rightly, he needs to start developing understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: And yeah, so he goes on saying, what are the things he should not attend to, that he attends to?
[SPEAKER_00]: There are things such that when he attends to them, the unarisen taint of sensual desire arises in him, and the arisen taint of sensual desire increases.
[SPEAKER_00]: The unarisen taint of being arises in him, and the arisen taint of being increases.
[SPEAKER_00]: The unarisen taint of ignorance arises in him, and the arisen taint of ignorance increases.
[SPEAKER_00]: And obviously, consequently, the things that he should attend to,
[SPEAKER_00]: But he doesn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Things that, when he attends to them, the unarisen taint of sensuality does not arise, and the arisen taint of sensuality is abandoned.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same goes for the being, the taint of being, and the taint of ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he keeps on attending improperly.
[SPEAKER_00]: He keeps... he keeps attending unwisely, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, without a proper perspective.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he ends up thinking, was I in the past?
[SPEAKER_00]: Was I not in the past?
[SPEAKER_00]: What was I in the past?
[SPEAKER_00]: How was I in the past?
[SPEAKER_00]: Having been what, what did I become?
[SPEAKER_00]: Shall I be in the future?
[SPEAKER_00]: Shall I not be in the future?
[SPEAKER_00]: What shall I be in the future?
[SPEAKER_00]: How shall I be in the future?
[SPEAKER_00]: Having been what, what shall I become in the future?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or else, he is inwardly perplexed about the present.
[SPEAKER_00]: Am I?
[SPEAKER_00]: Am I not?
[SPEAKER_00]: What am I?
[SPEAKER_00]: How am I?
[SPEAKER_00]: Where has this thing... where has this being come from?
[SPEAKER_00]: Where will it go?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you might notice all these questions have one thing in common, which is they're completely self-centered.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, obviously, this is the... quite a condensed...
[SPEAKER_00]: Paragraph.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not... it's not that the person actually sits on the chair and starts thinking in such a crude manner.
[SPEAKER_00]: Was I in the past?
[SPEAKER_00]: Was I not?
[SPEAKER_00]: These questions should be understood on a subtle level of implication, whereby when you're thinking about something in the past or something about the future, you're thinking in a self-centered manner.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, you don't question your own self in it, in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're questioning the content of your experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: You might be even doubting, but what you're not doubting is that there has been some sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not doubting that I was in the past.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or rather, you're not doubting the I of the question, was I in the past?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, was I in the past or was I not in the past?
[SPEAKER_00]: Either way, the question revolves around the self-centered sense of I.
[SPEAKER_00]: And those questions, as the Buddha said, see, there is no, like, answer to them in the sense of, oh, you must figure it out, answer to every individual question here that's been read.
[SPEAKER_00]: On the contrary, these questions arise, or rather, sense of self and self-centeredness arises as a result of improperly attending to sensuality, nature of being, and ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: And actually, yeah, here it says, the next paragraph, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: is the actual truth.
[SPEAKER_00]: My self does not exist as the actual truth.
[SPEAKER_00]: The view I perceive self with self will arise in him.
[SPEAKER_00]: The view that I perceive not-self with self arise in him.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or the view I perceive self with not-self arise in him.
[SPEAKER_00]: And as Jnana-Vedā-Thera pointed out, what Puthujjana cannot develop is the view that I perceive not-self with not-self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if that arises in him, then he'll be a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he remains fully self-centered and established in his wrong self-view as a result of wrongly attending to these three types of taints, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: The sensuality, being, nature of phenomena and ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: And because he ends up developing self-view, he becomes subjected to aging and death, sorrow, lamentation, pain, grief and despair.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, now, a well-taught noble disciple, who does see noble ones, who is skilled and trained in the dhamma, who sees true men and is skilled and trained in the dhamma, understands what things should be attended to and what things should not be attended to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Since that is so, he does not attend to those things he should not attend and he attends to those things he should attend.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it goes the same, to repeat, what are the things he should not attend are the things that lead to increasing of sensuality, being, and ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: And things that are fit for attention are things that lead to decreasing of sensuality, being, and ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, because
[SPEAKER_00]: Because he's been attending properly, he attends... he can attend further.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is suffering, he attends properly.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is the origin of suffering, he attends properly.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is the cessation of suffering, he attends properly.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is the way leading to the cessation of suffering, when he attends wisely in this way.
[SPEAKER_00]: These fetters are abandoned in him.
[SPEAKER_00]: Personality view, doubt, and adhering to behavior and duties.
[SPEAKER_00]: So...
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I'm just looking for a Pali word here.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's... yeah, so... this is... this is already... yeah, this is talking about Ārya-sāvaka, who clearly, see, hasn't become a sotāpanna yet, but already learned how to attend to things like an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: As the Mūla Pariyāya Sutta 1, Majjhima Nikāva 1 said.
[SPEAKER_00]: By the way, this is Majjhima Nikāva 2.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exit from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in Ārya-sāvaka,
[SPEAKER_00]: By having understood what needs to be attended properly, having understood what proper attention is, having and having having directly known what he's perceiving, then he can practice proper attention in regards to things as they present themselves, and bring the sensuality to decrease, being to decrease, and ignorance to decrease, and then he can also attend in the same manner about the nature of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: By doing so, he will become a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_00]: He will be free from the self-view, from doubt, and from holding on to virtue and duty or behavior and duties.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then it says,
[SPEAKER_00]: Furthermore, because a noble disciple reflects thus, I'm endowed with the nature of an individual who possesses right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the nature of an individual who possesses right view?
[SPEAKER_00]: This is the nature of the individual who possesses right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Although he may commit some kind of offense for which a means of rehabilitation has been laid down,
[SPEAKER_00]: Still, he at once confesses, reveals and discloses it to the teacher or to wise companions in the holy life.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having done that, he enters upon restraint for the future.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, he is his virtue.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's not doing his virtue.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's not keeping his virtue.
[SPEAKER_00]: He has become it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why if, say, lapsed in his mindfulness or some old habits that are still strong or something and circumstances press him and he commits some sort of offense for which he needs to go through rehabilitation, he will confess it and reveal it and disclose it to the wise ones, as in to other āryas, to arahants, to his teacher or similar.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, eh... he cannot remain concealing it, because he is it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not optional for him.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it says, just as a young tender infant, lying prone, once draws back his hand or his foot on a live coal, so too, that is the nature of an individual who possesses the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, back to Majjhima Niqab 4.
[SPEAKER_00]: There are Brahmins, some recluses in Brahmins, who perceive day when it is night, and night when it is day.
[SPEAKER_00]: I say that, on their part, this is an abiding in delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I perceive night when it is night, and day when it is day.
[SPEAKER_00]: Rightly speaking, worried to be said of anyone, being not subjected to delusion, has appeared in the world for the welfare and happiness of many, out of compassion for the world, for the good, welfare, happiness of gods and humans.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is me, indeed, that rightly speaking, this should be...
[SPEAKER_00]: It is of me, indeed, that rightly speaking, this should be said.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this comes back to that, eh... as we open this, the... the perception, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: Often, you probably... people must have come across pretty much denying what you perceive as a way of dealing, as a way of overcoming.
[SPEAKER_00]: What you perceive.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you will want to overcome it, because you're bothered by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, people perceive things that cause them suffering and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they think that the way out of suffering is to start denying the perception.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you often hear that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even in the latest schools of Buddhism, people would deny the reality of things.
[SPEAKER_00]: They would say they're constantly changing on a subatomic level and whatnot.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what you're looking at, it's not really a real thing, which is just another word... another way of sort of veiling things in a metaphysical ignorance of... of Maya and all Hindu's teachings.
[SPEAKER_00]: whereby the the reality is hidden behind the appearances.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, the Buddha says, well, that's... whichever way you take that, it's going to be abiding in delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: When there is night, he perceives night.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means, what he perceives, he sees that as a real thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there was never a problem to begin with.
[SPEAKER_00]: As again, Majjhima Nikāh 1, Mūla Parīyā, as we read in the beginning, it's not the perceiving that's the... well, sorry, it's not what you perceive that's the problem, the problem is in your act of perceiving, that misconceives what's being perceived.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can try and examine and investigate as much as you want the content and the molecular compounds of the contents of your perception.
[SPEAKER_00]: Still, that's not bringing you an inch closer to understanding the nature of perception, which is see...
[SPEAKER_00]: In order to understand the nature of perception, you need to be... you need to stop being concerned with the content of your perception.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, first, you restrain the unwholesome content.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you overcome the wholesome content through discerning the nature of what you're perceiving, not what you're perceiving.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there was... this was Majjhima 4.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah, here is an interesting passage.
[SPEAKER_00]: Quite useful to remind yourself of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Majjhima Nikaya 8.
[SPEAKER_00]: Cunda.
[SPEAKER_00]: The idea that one who has himself sunk into the mud can pull out another who has sunk into the mud.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's quite obvious.
[SPEAKER_00]: Unless a person is at least a sotāpanna, as in somebody who is pertained to the direct knowledge of an arahant, as Mūla Parīyāya Sūtra said above, unless somebody has developed a right view, they cannot teach somebody else.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, puthujjana cannot lead another puthujjana out of a state of puthujjana.
[SPEAKER_00]: A person who is himself deep sinking into the mud, cannot take another one, who is also in that mud right next to him.
[SPEAKER_00]: They will be sinking together.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's important to maintain that criteria, because people tend to water it down through sort of an attitude of, well, I am a putujana, but for as long as I'm making this effort,
[SPEAKER_00]: My intentions are good.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't mean any harm.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that means I can help others.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you can help others in a very, very relative sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe point them to the suttas and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you actually think you can teach others in a way of... direct way out of suffering, without you yourself understanding the way out of suffering, that's a complete contradiction.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the best way to help others, the most compassionate way to help others, is to free yourself first.
[SPEAKER_00]: To recognize that first you need to step up, find a way out of the mud, the sinking mud.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when you do, then you will help others.
[SPEAKER_00]: You will know exactly how to help others.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then you might realize that some of them don't want to be helped.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the idea that one who has not sunk into the mud can pull out another who has sunk into the mud, that's possible.
[SPEAKER_00]: The idea that one who himself is unextinguished, untrained,
[SPEAKER_00]: Can help somebody else to become tame, trained and extinguished.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's impossible.